# Saurabh Bansal



mail@saurabhbansal.me



linkedin.com/in/bansal-saurabh



+44 115 888 0950



https://github.com/bansal-saurabh

## Summary

Technical Consultant with 9 years of experience in Industrial Automation (IIoT/MES), Software Engineering/ Implementation, Mobile App Development and Enterprise IT/Cloud Deployment. Certified in Microsoft Azure and Power Platform along with a Masters in Cloud computing.

Skilled in Agile delivery methodologies, Machine connectivity, Smart manufacturing, Internet of Things, Enterprise Java, Docker/Kubernetes, MongoDB, Android and Cloud native solutions.

## **Experience**



#### Technical Consultant

#### **FORCAM**

Jun 2019 - Present (2 years 8 months +)

- Technical Delivery Lead for multi-site roll out of Forcam's MES offering for major Aerospace and battery-tech manufacturers.
- Core consultant for global implementation of Digital Numerical Control and Machine Connectivity for one of the world's biggest medical devices manufacturer.
- Configuration, testing and 2nd level support of Forcam Force (IIOT/MES, Edge, SaaS) for industrial automation solutions.
- Implementation of bespoke customer functionality with Power platform, Scripting, Third-party libraries, and integration of Bridge API and SSO solutions (LDAP, OAuth, SAML).
- Manage cloud systems, pre-sales support, work with sales and marketing for demonstrations, conduct training workshops and create technical specification.

### Android/Web Developer

#### Freelance

Mar 2014 - Dec 2018 (4 years 10 months)

- Full-stack Web application development with NodeJS, ReactJS, Bootstrap, WordPress, JavaScript, PHP, and MySQL/MongoDB.
- Native and Hybrid Mobile application development with Java, Kotlin and React Native.
- Requirements gathering and specification development with Agile methodologies.
- Integration of several data sources, third-party systems and REST APIs.
- Extension of product features, bug-fixing and post-development life cycle support.



## **Network Engineer**

## Jindal Electro Systems

Jan 2018 - Jul 2018 (7 months)

- Research and implementation of networked solutions for CCTV security and GPS tracking systems.
- Support on-site technicians during hardware installation and equipment set-up.
- Troubleshoot & resolve network/hardware issue. and provide second level support.

IT Specialist

Jayess Builders Mar 2017 - Nov 2017 (9 months)

PHP Programmer

Freelance
Jul 2012 - Feb 2014 (1 year 8 months)

#### **Education**

Nottingham Trent University

Master of Science - MS, Cloud Computing 2018 - 2020

Nottingham Trent University

Diploma in Professional Practice 2019 - 2020

RIMT University

Bachelor of Technology - BTech, Computer Science 2008 - 2012

#### **Licenses & Certifications**

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Administrator Associate Microsoft
- **Microsoft Certified: Power Platform Fundamentals** Microsoft
- **G** Fundamentals of Digital Marketing Google
- IBM Certified: Rational Application Developer IBM

#### Skills

Java • JavaScript • Android • Microsoft SQL Server • Microsoft Azure • Microsoft Power Platform • DevOps • Kubernetes • Smart Manufacturing • Industry 4.0

#### **Honors & Awards**

University of the Year Scholarship - Nottingham Trent University
Mar 2019

Bridge API Power User - Forcam

Jan 2020